[XBOX SOUND]
Hello, and welcome to
The Official Xbox Podcast.
I'm your host, Tina Amini, and
we have a very special episode
today, as you can
probably tell by the fact
that, I'm joined by
Phil, Sarah, and Matt.
Welcome.
And we're going to talk
about some updates at Xbox.
We want to talk about
game exclusivity.
Activision Blizzard
now that they're a part of
our portfolio, how that might
be an impact on Game Pass.
And we want to talk
about hardware too
and how all of this fits
into the strategy at Xbox.
So where should we start, Phil?
Well, when we originally had
planned for this show starting
back in December,
I think we probably
would have started with
Activision Blizzard,
maybe talked a little
bit about the exclusivity
with some of the news coming
up, and then hardware.
But we've had some unforeseen
news that has come out.
So let's just go and tackle
the exclusivity question,
because I know it's on
the minds a lot of people.
We hear from the
community, and that's
an important input for us.
So we made the
decision that we're
going to take four games
to the other consoles--
just four games, not
a change to our kind
of fundamental
exclusive strategy.
We're making these decisions
for some specific reasons.
We make every decision, really,
with the long-term health
of Xbox in mind.
And long-term health of Xbox
means a growing platform,
our games performing, building
the best platform for creators,
reaching as many
players as we can.
We're always looking to learn as
a leadership team and to grow.
And we think this is an
interesting point in time
for us to use what some
of the other platforms
have right now to help
grow our franchises.
So we're going to do that.
TINA AMINI: So
these four titles--
what are they?
Can you say?
I'm not going to
name those games.
The teams that are
building those games
have announced plans that
are not too far away.
As we know, game teams
put a lot of energy
into their announcements
with the partners.
So I don't want to take
anything away from those teams.
So I won't be talking about
the titles specifically.
But I think when they come
out, it'll make sense.
TINA AMINI: Can we say
if either of those titles
are Starfield or Indiana Jones?
They are not Starfield
or Indiana Jones.
TINA AMINI: Well,
what was the criteria
in how the team was thinking
about selecting those four
titles?
Let me start a little
bit outside of that,
and then I'll get to the
four specific games that
we're talking about right,
now because the fundamental
decision driver for any
decision that we make,
anything we're going to talk
about today is the long-term
health of Xbox--
that we're running a
growing platform that
is reaching more players,
that our games are having
as much success as possible.
And I do have a
fundamental belief
that over the next
5 or 10 years,
exclusive games, games
that are exclusive to one
piece of hardware, are going to
be a smaller and smaller part
of the game industry.
And that's not
some great insight
because if you look
at the last 10 years
and what the biggest games are
today, it's a natural place--
whether it's one console
in PC, multiple consoles,
mobile, console, and PC--
you see big games landing
on multiple platforms.
And we want to be
a great platform
for creators that are trying
to realize that potential.
But now, back to the specifics
of the question on these four
specific titles.
We looked at games that
are over a year old.
So they've been on Xbox
and PC for a while.
A couple of the games are
community-driven games,
new games, kind of first
iterations of a franchise that
have reached their full
potential, let's say,
on Xbox and PC--
there's always growth,
franchises that we obviously
want to continue to invest in.
Part of having the ability
to continue to invest
is that the businesses behind
those franchises continue.
We think it's important that
these service-based games that
have communities behind them,
that they can have confidence
that they're going to
exist in the future.
So two of them kind of
community-driven games
that will end up
on other platforms
and give us the ability to
continue to invest in them.
We think that's great
for the business
and great for the communities--
more players to play with.
Two of the other games are
smaller games that were never
really meant to be built as
kind of platform exclusives
and all the fanfare
that goes around that,
but games that our teams
really wanted to go
build that we love
supporting creative endeavors
across our studios
regardless of size.
And as they've realized their
full potential on Xbox and PC,
we see an opportunity to
utilize the other platforms
as a place to just drive
more business value out
of those games,
allowing us to invest
in maybe future
iterations of those,
so sequals to those,
or just other games
like that in our portfolio.
And when we don't damage Xbox
and we can grow our business
using what other platforms
have to help us with that,
we're going to do that.
And that's really the story
behind these four games.
And last thing I'll
say looking forward,
I think there is an interesting
story for us of introducing
Xbox franchises to
players on other platforms
to get them more
interested in Xbox.
We think there's a good
brand value for Xbox there.
So four games, no
promise beyond that.
So if you're on
those other platforms
and you see these four
games coming, please
don't take it as some signal
that everything's coming.
It's not.
And we're going to learn.
TINA AMINI: So when
you are thinking
about the future and this
concept of live service games,
games that can benefit
from bigger audiences,
new audiences, how does
that apply to future titles
and how you're applying
that criteria there?
Yeah.
There's really no
fundamental change
to how we think
about exclusivity.
We just came out of
Developer Direct,
which was an awesome show where
we showed great games that
are coming to Xbox,
and PC, and cloud,
which really makes them
accessible to hundreds
of millions of people.
So we're really focused on a
couple platforms and what's
going to show up there.
But our key of
play the games you
want, with the people you
want, anywhere you want,
when everybody
plays, we all win--
these have been part of
our strategy for years
and will continue to be.
Our focus is on,
how do we continue
to grow the games industry by
reaching more players in more
places?
And how do we grow
Xbox as part of that--
Xbox as a hardware
platform, Xbox
as a publisher of
great games, and Xbox
as a platform for the
world's best creators.
And then knowing
that, how do we
think about our first
party games and Game Pass?
MATT BOOTY: Yeah.
Well, to build on what Phil just
said, one thing I would add--
you were talking about growth--
is just that we've seen this
inversion over the last five
years where it used to be that
the platform was the biggest
thing, and the games would
tuck in within the platform.
Today, big games like
a Roblox or a Fortnite
could actually be bigger
than any one platform.
And that really has changed the
way that we think about things.
So in the midst of all that,
I think we at First Party
can come back to some
core principles--
first, that all of our games
will be on the Xbox platform.
Second, all of our games will
go into Game Pass on day one.
And third, we know that
Game Pass will only
be available on Xbox.
So there's starting
points for us.
As Phil mentioned,
there are games today
that you can play that
only can be found on Xbox.
And at the same time, we want
to bring more of our games
to more players.
So we're going to
continue to look at that.
Kind of moving aside,
though, from some of those
and thinking more about,
what does it really
mean for the player?
To me, the two key things are
cross-play and cross-save.
Those things allow us to deliver
on the promise of Xbox, which
is play with your
friends where they are,
play on the devices you want,
play the games you want.
So that is really only
possible at a practical level
when you know that your
saves and your player
are going to be able to
move across all those parts.
So not all of our games
today are necessarily
built to take advantage of that.
There still will be
some games that don't.
As we bring more teams
into the Xbox family,
there's some catchup
to do as we get there.
But that cross-play,
cross-save is
so fundamental to
what we're doing.
And I think it's something
that we as First Party
get such a good benefit from
being so close to the platform.
Yeah, absolutely.
That's one of the things, like
you said, all of our games
are always in Game Pass.
And so I'm excited to
announce, with the coming
together that we had with
Activision Blizzard King,
that Activision
and Blizzard games
are coming to Game Pass
starting with Diablo IV
on March 28, which I'm super,
super excited to share today.
And it's all part
of our commitment
to make Xbox, the Xbox
experience, and the games
that we build as widely
available as possible.
So now the 34 million
Game Pass members
can all enjoy the fantastic
experience of Diablo IV.
TINA AMINI: Amazing.
Can we come back to the point--
Phil, you mentioned
at the top of this,
this isn't really a
change in strategy for us.
Can you recap for
me how it isn't?
Yeah.
And I thought both
Matt and Sarah
did a really nice job of
talking about what we're doing
on Xbox, where we're going.
If you take a platform feature
like Xbox Play Anywhere, which
has been a promise that we've
made on our first party games,
that you can buy our
game once, you're
going to get to play
across Xbox and Windows--
I think we're the only
platform that does this--
that makes it possible
for you not only to play
with your friends
wherever they are,
but to know that you actually
have multiple entitlements
to the games.
I think that's a
technology I'd love to see
applied to more platforms.
But it is this view
that people are
going to play Xbox
in multiple places,
whether it's play the games you
want with the people you want
anywhere you want,
whether it's content,
community, and cloud, whether
it's when everybody plays,
we all win--
we've had different
taglines different strategy
kind of words that
we've used, but always
with this view that Xbox
is a platform for creators
who want to reach
the most players.
Our investments in
xCloud, our investments
in franchises like Minecraft,
and now Call of Duty,
and other large
franchises so that we
learn how to build those.
This has been a strategy that
we've been on for, I'd say,
a decade.
It's not about one device.
It's not about games
in service of a device,
but, rather, the devices
that people want to play on
should be in service of making
the games as big and popular
as they possibly could be.
Because, really, a
healthy creator community
on Xbox, a healthy creator
community in gaming
all up is the thing that
all of us as Game Players
should be voting
for, because that's
the thing that will lead to
the best long-term success
and growth in this industry.
TINA AMINI: And my
understanding just
from listening, and
learning from you
three over the past
few weeks, just
understanding what's
happening with Xbox
is that we see trends
with player behavior
where people are playing
on multiple devices.
That is the reality.
And we have put some games out
on multiple platforms before.
So my understanding is that
that's been good for players.
How does that come
back to the business
with all of that in mind?
Yeah.
As you said, we have shipped
games on other platforms.
In fact, realistically,
if you look
with the addition of Activision
Blizzard and ZeniMax,
we're one of the largest game
publishers on PlayStation.
We're one of the largest
publishers on the Nintendo
Switch, especially when you
put Minecraft into the equation
as well.
And now, we're one of
the largest publishers
on mobile platforms as well.
And that's not something that
we want to back away from.
We want to continue to
be building great games
that millions and millions
of people can love
and that they can
play those games where
they want to go play.
But we do understand
the business success
that Xbox has to have.
Us as leaders in this
business, the system
today, the system
that all companies
that we play video games
from is a world of you've
got to be growing
your business--
growth in our Xbox
business is critical to
the long-term health of Xbox.
Many people know I've been
on Xbox for over 20 years,
and I want to make sure
Xbox is in the best
position for the next 20 years.
That means healthy player
community, healthy creator
community, and healthy business.
So when we look at opportunities
to allow more people to play,
more people to engage,
more people to buy,
more people to
subscribe, it's all about
putting Xbox in
the best position.
And our hardware is a
critical component of that.
The absolute best experience
somebody has on Xbox
is hardware that our team
builds and that people play on.
But that's not going
to be everybody.
We fully accepted
that we're going
to have Xbox players across
all kinds of devices.
So I think a lot
of people think
about 2023 is this
incredible year for gaming.
And in a lot of ways, it was.
There was some really
amazing releases
that I think we all enjoyed.
But what were the signals behind
the scenes that maybe indicated
how we wanted to look
at the future of Xbox
and how we keep up
with the industry?
Yeah, such a good question.
And I think as people who
care about the industry, which
I assume is people
who are watching this,
it was an amazing year--
some great launches.
Some of the games that
I think will stand
the test of time and
people will be talking
about a decade from now.
But it's an industry
that didn't really grow.
And what happens when an
industry doesn't grow?
You end up with some job
eliminations, which we had.
We had even our
own hard decisions
to make about
building a sustainable
business for ourselves, but in
no way were we alone in that.
When you think about
a healthy industry,
I want players who
believe that they
will find the best games on
the platforms that they love.
I want people who invest
their careers in working here
to feel like this is a place
that they can be successful.
And that really is
down to being part
of an industry that is growing.
If you listen to
Lisa Su, the AMD CEO,
she'll say that
AMD-powered consoles
are likely to decline in 2024.
I think there's an amazing
set of games coming in 2024,
but if we don't get to
growing as an industry,
the industry will struggle.
And today, there's
really two choices
on how do you grow the industry.
Do you say, I have a
fixed number of players,
the players that we have
today, and do I find new ways
to monetize those players to
get more money from the players
that I have?
Or do you think
about, how do I expand
the business I have
by finding new players
and adding those to the base
of players that already play?
Our focus on Xbox
for the last decade
has really been on
that latter point
of, how do we make
sure Xbox is growing?
Growing for our players,
growing for our creators
so those people
are finding success
on our platform, which
will grow the Xbox business
and put Xbox in a position
to be very strong for years
and decades to come.
TINA AMINI: Matt,
earlier, you were
talking about these growing
gaming communities, how they're
incredibly large and comparable
on such a different level
when we think about console
audiences-- like you mentioned
Roblox, you mentioned Fortnite.
So we're obviously thinking
about our responsibility,
our hardware responsibility in
supporting the growth of gaming
communities.
How has that actually
shown up for the players?
Are there other games we can
speak to from our portfolio?
Well, as Phil mentioned, two
of the biggest ones for us,
Call of Duty and Minecraft--
they are driven just from
the bottom-up by the communities
of people that play those
games, which is so great.
Think about it, for
the player community,
it comes down to,
where are the friends?
Where are the people
you play with?
And then equally important
is, where have you built up
your library of games, right?
Where have you invested?
Where is that library?
I think those two
things probably
are some of the biggest
influences on where
people choose to play and what
devices they choose to play.
Absolutely.
When we think about on the
other side, the developer side,
just any game developer
wants their game
to find the biggest
audience possible.
That's just the nature
of building a game.
You want people to
enjoy and participate
in what you've made.
And I think we're in a unique
position to deliver on that
just because we are the
platform-- we build hardware.
We've got a first
party games group.
And then we've got a system
that ties that together that
brings together your
friends, your progression,
your achievements, all of that.
And I think that's
really what has
contributed to the
momentum behind some
of these communities.
SARAH BOND: Yeah, absolutely.
When you just step
back and you look
at the history of
the industry, we've
moved from a place where it
used to be that someone built
and launched a game to
accelerate hardware,
to actually the things
we do with our hardware
and with our platform
are all in service
of making those games bigger.
And we think about that
across all of the investments
we make-- the consoles
we build, the investments
we do with things
like cross-play,
cross-progression, the things
that we're doing with cloud.
How do we actually give more
options to game creators
so they can have the
greatest success?
I think one of the fun
recent examples about this
is actually Palworld.
Palworld was able to launch.
They were a game preview.
They launched in Game Pass.
They also simultaneously
launched in Steam.
And so the combination of
those things, Pocket Pair
was able to have this
outsized success.
And it was the largest third
party Game Pass launch ever.
And that's all because
we give creators
options on how they
can launch their games.
We've got subscription.
We've got retail.
We've got free to play.
We've got game preview.
We have the consoles.
We have our experience on PC.
And they can access
all of those things.
And when we step
back and we just
look at the performance
of our platform all up,
we know it's working.
We're at the highest
level of users on console,
the highest level
of users on PC,
the highest level of
users on cloud ever.
We have double-digit growth
rate on PC and cloud,
places where we're
enabling creators
to actually reach new players
beyond the console ecosystem.
And that's why we're
leaning into it
and doing more, because
we see all those signals.
So we're talking
about the role
that hardware plays for
creators, for the games,
and those communities.
What about the
role that hardware
plays for us as a
business, for Xbox?
When we look at our
hardware, it really is,
and Phil said this
earlier, it's where
you get the most flagship,
seminal experience of Xbox.
And it also represents
a developer target.
Our developers can build
the specs of our hardware,
and we invest to make sure
when they do that the games are
going to run great
on our hardware,
but they're also going
to be able to be accessed
across any screen because of all
the other investments we make.
So we're giving them
an easy way to access
as many players as possible.
And we actually have more
creators right now building
for Xbox than ever
before, thousands of them,
by nature of those investments.
And we got more to come.
There's some exciting stuff
coming out in hardware
that we're going to
share this holiday.
And we're also invested in
the next generation roadmap.
And what we're really focused on
there is delivering the largest
technical leap you
will have ever seen
in a hardware generation, which
makes it better for players
and better for creators and the
visions that they're building.
TINA AMINI: And then when we're
talking about hardware, too,
there's these other
considerations
that are really important
to our community,
probably to each one
of ourselves as well.
When you talk about
library, because I
want to dig in on that
a little bit more--
as we talk about cloud and the
wider entertainment industry,
there's conversations
about streaming.
How is that impacting
how I own my content
that I've invested in?
So what can we say
about our stance
around game preservation?
Yeah.
One of the highlights for
me of being in this position
was getting to stand on
stage when we announced back
compat coming to Xbox One.
It was fantastic.
People were reading
the teleprompter
before I could read,
I'm a slow reader,
and just feeling the
energy in the auditorium
as we were saying
that, and online.
One of the cues, I think, us
as being part of Microsoft
take is looking at Windows,
and how Windows, over decades,
has maintained software
compatibility with things
that are built on it.
Like, I can still go back
and play some of the games
that I love playing on
Windows from decades ago
and it will still run.
And we try to bring that
same view to consoles.
It's harder in console
because the line
between what the hardware is
and what the game is in consoles
is traditionally
tighter, which you end up
doing these generational
compatibilities
that we've built. But I will
say compatibility, the ability
to not only play the games,
but my saves are still there
with our cloud save systems,
to try to keep the services up
as long as we can so
that people can play
is a tenet of what
we are as Xbox.
It's at our foundation.
And when we look at future
hardware generations
and what we're going
to support, making sure
that we respect, which is
the word I use "respect"
the investments that people
have made in Xbox going forward
is fundamental.
And the fact that
you get entitlements
when you buy a game from
us on both Windows and Xbox
also means you have
the ability to play
that game across a multitude
of devices, which I think
furthers the compatibility
of the games that you own.
Can we go back to what
Xbox stands for today?
I think we've pretty much
covered all of the elements.
But if you could
break it down for me.
When you play on Xbox,
what we're saying is
you're playing on
a platform where
you know the biggest
games in the world
are always going to be.
You're playing on
a platform where
you get to access Game Pass.
And all of the games from our
incredible range of studios
will always launch
in Game Pass day one.
And you're playing on a platform
that's dedicated to you--
player-first features--
cross-play, cross-save,
cross-progression,
backwards compatibility,
being able to play your games
in your library anywhere
you want because
of the investments
that we make in cloud gaming.
And so you're playing somewhere
where you're investing
and you know you get to
take the games forward
with you and across all of
the screens where you are.
And I think most importantly,
Xbox is a place where you know
when you're investing
in Xbox, you're
investing somewhere that is
dedicated to making games more
successful and creators
more successful,
so that they can invest more to
bring even better experiences
to you all of the time.
Yeah.
That investment in
the studios is so--
and we feel that as part of
first party with the platform
proximity-- it's
kind of amazing now
to look out across all
the studios that we've got
and just be reminded
that we're now
one of the biggest development
organizations in the industry.
What does that mean for players?
It means that the
biggest games are going
to continue to come to Xbox.
And this 2024, the
year coming up,
we've got more than 10
major releases coming up--
great stuff.
Hellblade 2, they've
got Diablo expansion,
they've got Avowed, Ara,
the Indiana Jones game,
and there's more in
development, which
I think we're going to be able
to share more about at our June
showcase coming up pretty soon.
Well, I guess I should get
ready to work on that show.
[LAUGHTER]
Well, thank you all for showing
up on the podcast today.
And we'll see the rest
of you, this June.
Yeah.
Thanks, Tina.
Thank you.
[XBOX SOUND]